<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 John Willis <143434770+CerberusWolfie@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 BombasterDS2 <shvalovdenis.workmail@gmail.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
# Chief Medical Officer (CMO) SOP
This is the list of procedures, responsibilities, and duties of the [color=#1b67a5][bold]Chief Medical Officer[/bold][/color] of this station.

1. The Chief Medical Officer is highly encouraged to carry a regular Defibrillator or a Compact Defibrillator on their person at all times.

2. The Chief Medical Officer is permitted to carry a telescopic baton, flash, and syringe gun at all times.
<Box>The syringe gun should not contain harmful chemicals at any point except during emergencies.</Box>
<!--, such as Nuclear Operatives, Blob, and/or Delta Alert. # Omu, remove refernces to metashielded things.

-->3. The Chief Medical Officer is not permitted to allow the creation of any explosive, lacerating, poisonous, caustic, or otherwise harmful non-medicinal mixture for any purpose other than the synthesis of medicine without express consent from the [color=#1b67a5][bold]Captain[/bold][/color] or, failing that, the presence of a clear and urgent danger to the integrity of the station. Vestine or its derivatives found in Chemistry from a non-Nanotrasen source must be reported to [color=#ba292c][bold]Security[/bold][/color] immediately.
  <!-- , except of course in situations where Chemical Implants are required. # Omu, remove SS13 reference of Chemical Implants; parity added with Chemist SOP

-->4. The Chief Medical Officer is not permitted to allow the release of any virus without a full list of its symptoms, and they must have a vaccine of the virus on hand to be given out on request.
<Box>The virus may not have any harmful symptoms whatsoever unless the benefits of the virus neutralize the symptoms. Neutral or harmless symptoms are permitted.</Box><!-- Omu, relaxed "any harmful symptoms" to allow for minor damaging but majorly healing viruses
Omu, rewording and parity change
-->5. The Chief Medical Officer must ensure that all deceased station personnel are revived, cloned, or given a successful brain transplant unless the individual is under a Do Not Resuscitate order (DNR). Individuals under a DNR should be placed in the Morgue with documentation of the DNR. [bold]Bodies of Transit Prisoners must return to Central Command even if under a DNR.[/bold] In addition, the Chief Medical Officer must make sure that the Morgue does not contain cloneable corpses.
  <Box>The Chief Medical Officer is not permitted to intentionally delay the revival of personnel without permission from the [color=#1b67a5][bold]Head of Security[/bold][/color], and the Captain must not overrule this. Additionally, the Captain may, with good cause, unilaterally order the prevention of revival of individuals. The [bold][color=#ba292c]Warden[/color][/bold] or Head of Security may order a reasonable delay in revival of a prisoner so that Security can apprehend the prisoner. Failure to follow this Guideline may be considered Prevention of Revival.</Box>
  <!-- Omu, updated
-->6. The Chief Medical Officer is responsible for swiftly setting up Cloning, the Medical Biofabricator, and the Biomass Reclaimer in a location easily accessible by all Medical personnel. In addition, the Chief Medical Officer must coordinate with Atmospherics to ensure the functionality of Cryo Pods. It is also recommended (but not necessary) to designate a cryogenics area within Medbay for heavily insulated species, such as Vulpkanin, and to coordinate with Engineering to construct it.
  <Box>Failure to attempt to follow this Guideline within ten (10) minutes is to be considered a breach of Standard Operating Procedure. Cryo Pods must be operational within thirty (30) minutes or else be considered a breach of Standard Operating Procedure.</Box>
<!-- Omu, added Virologist reference and explicit notice that the CMO should be doing chem/viro work
-->7. The Chief Medical Officer is expected to assist Medical Doctors, Chemists, and Virologists when necessary, up to and including assuming their roles in their absence. The Chief Medical Officer must ensure that the Medical Fridge is sufficiently stocked as according to the Chemist’s SOP and that Viral Outbreaks are eradicated swiftly.
<!-- Omu, parity change
-->8. The Chief Medical Officer may request to sit in during a Psychologist's therapy meeting [bold]but is not entitled to[/bold] if the client refuses. If the client accepts, then the Chief Medical Officer is under the same confidentiality agreement as the Psychologist. [bold]Breaching confidentiality is grounds for demotion.[/bold]
  <!-- Omu, verbiage
-->9. The Chief Medical Officer is expected to treat Command Personnel over regular Medical Personnel when possible.
  <!-- Omu, added for parity with Doctor/Intern SOP 14
-->10. If requested to during elevated levels of need, such as in situations where Red Alert is called, the Chief Medical Officer is expected to guide the reprioritization of healing based on crew hierarchy and the current situation.

</Document>
