<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 John Willis <143434770+CerberusWolfie@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->


<Document>
# Chemist SOP
This is the list of procedures, responsibilities, and duties of the [color=#42636d][bold]Chemist[/bold][/color] of this station.<!-- Omu, near-complete overhaul of this document to update for SS14

-->1. The Chemist must ensure that the Medical Fridge (or equivalent) is stocked with at least enough medication to handle Brute, Burn, Airloss, Toxin, and Genetic damage. This takes priority over non-medical requests for chemicals.
<Box>Failure to, at the very least, [bold]attempt[/bold] to follow this Guideline within thirty (30) minutes is to be considered a breach of Standard Operating Procedure. In handling a breach of this Guideline, it is [bold]strongly[/bold] recommended to ask first why it seems that no progress was made before complaining. Chemistry is a difficult subject; do not make it more difficult for Chemists to work.</Box>

2. The Chemist must ensure that medication is appropriately labeled with its name or abbreviation, the overdose limit, and what type of damage the medication heals. Additional information, such as the amount of damage healed or if a medication is toxic, is highly recommended.

3. The Chemist is not permitted to leave Chemistry unattended if the Medical Fridge (or equivalent) is devoid of medication, except in such a case that Chemistry is unusable or if Welding Fuel must be brought to Chemistry.

4. The Chemist is not permitted to create any explosive, lacerating, poisonous, caustic, or otherwise harmful non-medicinal mixture for any purpose other than the synthesis of medicine without express consent from the [color=#1b67a5][bold]Captain[/bold][/color], the [color=#1b67a5][bold]Chief Medical Officer[/bold][/color] with authorization from the Captain, or, failing that, the presence of a clear and urgent danger to the integrity of the station. If any of these chemicals are produced, they are to be disposed of immediately unless the prior exception applies.
<Box>Failure to follow this Guideline within one (1) minute is to be considered a breach of Standard Operating Procedure.</Box>

5. The Chemist is not permitted to experiment with Vestine or any derivative. Exceptions for Vestine may be given for Nanotrasen-provided Vestine or at the presence of a clear and urgent danger to the integrity of the station. Any Chemist who finds Vestine in one of their colleague’s devices should report it [bold]IN SECRET[/bold] immediately to [color=#ba292c][bold]Security[/bold][/color] and the Chief Medical Officer.

6. The Chemist is not permitted to produce alcoholic beverages except if requested by a [color=#388c34][bold]Bartender[/bold][/color] to do so.

7. The Chemist is allowed to produce narcotics as long as there is a reasonable backstock of medication in the Medical Fridge (or equivalent) for treating ailments of all types, including serious wounds from radioactive or caustic substances; viral and bacterial diseases; reversing rotting; and eye, brain, and mental/emotional damage. It is strongly recommended that the Chemist produce medication to combat drunkenness and hallucinations. [bold]The Chemist is not permitted to produce medication to heal Holy damage without permission from the station’s [color=#388c34]Chaplain[/color].[/bold] <!-- Omu, defined when chemists can make narcotics, and chappy must give permissions to make umbroxol

-->8. If there are no other Medical staff present in the Medbay and there are unattended patients requiring treatment, the Chemist must treat them as a Medical Doctor would. The Chemist is expected to follow the same guidelines as the [color=#42636d][bold]Medical Doctor[/bold][/color] when operating in the Medical Treatment Room or performing Surgery.
</Document>

