<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 John Willis <143434770+CerberusWolfie@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
# Medical Doctor/Intern SOP
This is the list of procedures, responsibilities, and duties of the [color=#42636d][bold]Medical Doctor[/bold][/color] and [color=#42636d][bold]Medical Intern[/bold][/color] of this station.

<!-- Omu, added vox/plasmaman inclusivity
-->1. Though not mandatory, it is recommended that Medical Doctors wear Sterile Masks/internals and Latex/Nitrile gloves when handling patients.
<Box>This Guideline becomes mandatory during Viral Outbreaks [bold]and[/bold] when performing [bold][italic]Surgeries[/italic][/bold].</Box>

<!-- Omu, verbiage
-->2. Medical Interns should focus on tending to patients that require light care and helping other qualified Medical staff in whatever they require.
<Box>If necessary, they may stand in for regular Medical Doctor duties.</Box><!-- Omu, mild verbiage changes

-->3. Medical Doctors must ensure there is at least one (1) Defibrillator charged and available for use in the Exam Room (or wherever the main treatment area may be).
<!-- Omu, minor changes

-->4. Medical Doctors must maintain the entirety of Medbay in a hygienic state. This includes (but is not limited to) cleaning organic residue, fluids, and/or corpses.
<Box>Janitorial Services should be requested for major spills.</Box> <!-- Omu, minor changes

  Omu, parity and moved a clause here
-->5. Medical Doctors must ensure that all deceased station personnel are revived, cloned, or given a successful brain transplant unless the individual is under a Do Not Resuscitate order (DNR). Individuals under a DNR should be placed in the Morgue with documentation of the DNR. In addition, Medical Doctors must make sure that the Morgue does not contain cloneable corpses.<!--

  Omu, added mention of cryo pods/vulp cryo + stasis beds/tables
-->6. When working on corpses, Medical Doctors are heavily encouraged to use stasis beds/operating tables to prevent rot from occurring, though once revived, the formerly deceased should be transferred to a bed without stasis capability. Medical Doctors must place all corpses inside body bags and/or freezers to preserve their state when unable to be worked on immediately.
  <Box>In extreme overload, the Morgue and/or Cryo Pods (or alternatives) may be used for preservation, but corpses should be checked for [bold][italic]souls[/italic][/bold] to ensure they can be revived.</Box>
<!-- # Omu, updated

-->7. Medical Doctors, in conjunction with other Medical staff, must ensure that Cloning is stocked with at least 100 units of Biomass at any given time. It is highly encouraged to store excess biomass in a Medical Biofabricator until needed. Medical Doctors must also verify before cloning that any body to be cloned has zero (0) Genetic damage.

8. Medical Doctors must certify that all cloned personnel are properly transferred to their new cloned body and fully healed before release, ensuring that any damage from the cloning process is mended.<!-- Omu, minor verbiage

-->9. Medical Doctors are not permitted to leave Medbay to perform recreational activities if there are unattended patients requiring treatment.
<!-- Omu, “Internal Bleeding” replaced with brute/burn/bone/organ damage

-->10. Medical Doctors should take patients to Surgery in order to operate on them if they have severe localized brute, burn, bone, and/or organ damage.
<!-- Omu, minor changes

-->11. Medical Doctors are not obligated to treat patients who are actively and intentionally harming themselves. If treated, refer the patient to the on-station [color=#42636d][bold]Psychologist[/bold][/color] if one is present.

<!-- Omu, added explicit confirmation that MDs can be virologists in emergencies
-->12. In the case that there is no [color=#42636d][bold]Virologist[/bold][/color] on station and a Viral Outbreak occurs, available Medical Doctors are allowed to assume the duties of a Virologist until one arrives or the Viral Outbreak has been eradicated.

<!-- Omu, added #13 and #14
-->13. Medical Doctors are strongly recommended to use Medical HUDs or their derivatives to quickly triage incoming patients' vitals. Should the HUD display a patient's vitals as critical, that patient should be stabilized as a priority over treating patients in a non-critical state.
<Box>Emergency Medipens are excellent at stabilizing patients, as they contain Atropine, but they are somewhat limited in quantity. Ideally, they should be reserved for patients in a critical state who will imminently die; however, a wasted Emergency Medipen is better than a dead patient. Should the need arise, it is permitted to use a patient's provided Emergency Medipen found in their survival box.</Box>

14. It is expected that treatment of [color=#1e7f28][bold]Central Command[/bold][/color] officials be prioritized first, especially the [color=#1b67a5][bold]Nanotrasen Representative[/bold][/color]. The [color=#1b67a5][bold]Blueshield Officer[/bold][/color] is the ultimate medical authority of [color=#1b67a5][bold]Command[/bold][/color] and should not be disturbed. It is in the Medical Doctor's best judgement otherwise to determine whom to treat first, but during elevated levels of need, such as in situations where Red Alert is called, healing may be reprioritized based on crew hierarchy and the current situation. The Chief Medical Officer is expected to guide the reprioritization if requested to do so.
</Document>

